Guide to the James William Fesler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James William Fesler papers
1918-1991
MS 207
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24.75
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, reports, memoranda, research material, clippings and photographs documenting the activities of James W. Fesler, as professor of political science at Yale University, as a participant in professional associations, and as a consultant on commissions appointed by the state of Connecticut, the United States government and the United Nations. His papers on the activities of the War Production Board (1941-1946) are particularly full and include correspondence, reports, charts and photographs.
Fesler, James W. (James William), 1911-2005
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James W. Fesler, 1965-1995, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 1988-M-041, Box 5 (letters of recommendation) is restricted until January 1, 2055 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
James W. Fesler was assistant to the executive secretary, War Production Board from 1941-1943, and chief of the Policy Analysis and Records Branch from 1943-1945. He served as historian of the War Production Board from 1945-1946. From 1935-1951, Fesler taught political science at the University of North Carolina, and from 1951-1979 he was a member of the department of political science at Yale University. He was also a visiting professor at the University of Minnesota and the University of California at Berkeley.
Scope and Contents
The original 1965 accession covers the period from 1941 to 1956, and is related mainly to the work of James William Fesler while he served on the War Production Board as Assistant to the Executive Secretary from 1941 to 1943, Chief of the Policy Analysis and Records Branch from 1943 to 1945, and War Production Board Historian from 1945 to 1946. During this period, James Fesler was in close contact with the United States War Production Program. His papers are contained in five manuscript boxes, three of which are correspondence. In addition to correspondence between various War Production officials and other government officials, these three boxes contain memoranda, press releases, and the minutes of War Production Board meetings. The two remaining boxes pertain to the War Production Board and include confidential reports, miscellaneous material, reports from other government agencies, miscellaneous notes of James Fesler, writings of Fesler and others concerning war production, charts, photographs, printed material on war production, and the War Production Board History Project.
Later additions to the papers document Fesler's participation on the committees of various academic organizations, particularly the American Society for Public Administration (ASPA) and the American Political Science Association, his activities as a professor of political science at Yale University and his service on commissions appointed by the state of Connecticut, the United States government and the United Nations. Included are the papers of the Committee on Europe of the Comparative Administration Group of the ASPA, correspondence of the Connecticut Committee on the Structure of State Government (Files Committee), files on various Yale administrative and faculty committees and the United Nations group on Administrative Decentralization for Development (1961). Also papers relating to various United States government commissions (1936-1967) working on administrative reorganization of the federal government.
Philosophy; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Educators; Political scientists; Ngô, Đình Diệm, 1901-1963; Batt, William Loren, 1885-1965; Belsley, G. Lyle (Gilbert Lyle), 1905-; Boeschenstein, Harold, 1896-1972; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986; Brownlow, Louis, 1879-1963; Davis, Donald Derby, 1888-1950; Deane, Charles Bennett, 1898-1969; Durham, Carl Thomas, 1892-1974; Eberstadt, Ferdinand; Fesler, James W. (James William), 1911-2005; Graham, George A. (George Adams), 1904-2005; Gulick, Luther Halsey, 1865-1918; Hechler, Ken, 1914-2016; Hill, Arthur Cheney Clifton, 1903-; Knowlson, James S., 1883-1959; Knudsen, William S., 1879-1948; Krug, Julius A. (Julius Albert), 1907-1970; Lawton, Frederick J. (Frederick Joseph), 1900-1975; Lilienthal, David Eli, 1899-1981; Maloney, Francis Thomas, 1894-1945; Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1887-1976; Nelson, Donald Marr, 1888-1959; Smith, Willis, 1887-1953; Stark, Harold R. (Harold Raynsford), 1880-1972; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Stoke, Harold W. (Harold Walter), 1903-1982; Symington, Stuart, 1901-1988; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Wilson, Charles Erwin, 1890-1961; Yust, Walter, 1894-1960; United Nations ( Commissions); United States. War Production Board; Yale University Press; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale Corporation; Yale University. Department of Political Science
- Original Accession, 1941-1956
  - Correspondence (including minutes of meetings, etc.), 1941-1944 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (including minutes of meetings, etc.), 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (including minutes of meetings, etc.), 1947-1956 (Box 3)
  - Confidential War Production Board Reports (Box 4)
  - Material relating to War Production and the War Production Board (Box 4)
  - Writings by James Fesler and others concerning War Production (Box 4)
  - Charts and Photographs (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Government Reports (Box 5)
  - Amendments to the Taft-Hartley Act (Box 5)
  - Notes of James Fesler (Box 5)
  - Printed Material and Newspaper-Clippings (Box 5)
- Additional Material, Circa 1940-1966; Accession 1968-M-001; 3 linear feet (2 paige, 2 archive)
  - Recommendation letters, pre-1951 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation letters, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation letters, A-K, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation letters, N-Z, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (personal), A-Z, 1950-1951, 1954-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (personal), A-Z, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - American Political Science Association (APSA):
    - Nominating committee, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Nomination committee, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Program committee and Washington committee, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Panel- State and local government, 1953 September (Box 2)
    - Public administration, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Panel- State and local government, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Committee on research need and resources in public administration, Circa 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Citizens for a Connecticut Constitutional Convention:
    - General, Circa 1954-1960 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and membership, Circa 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Center for Information on America (CIA):
    - Overall program, Circa 1955-1965 (Box 2)
    - Grass roots guide, circa 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - Editorial advisory committee, circa 1965 (Box 2)
  - Inter-University Case Program (ICP):
    - General program, circa 1965 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, circa 1965 (Box 2)
    - Regulatory committee, circa 1965 (Box 2)
    - Committee on the regulatory process, circa 1965 (Box 2)
    - Nominating committee, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of meetings, committee reports, case listings, circa 1965 (Box 2)
  - Yale College, circa 1950-1964 (Box 2)
  - Yale College:
    - Yale and Government Program: faculty advisory committee, circa 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Washington Summer Intern advisory committee, circa 1960-1962 (Box 3)
    - Politics and economics comprehensive, 1959 May (Box 3)
    - Graduate program, political science, circa 1957-1962 (Box 3)
    - Graduate school program, circa 1956-1962 (Box 3)
    - Graduate students, circa 1954-1962 (Box 3)
    - Herbert Jacob-German admin., circa 1957-1962 (Box 3)
    - Robert C. Fried-Italian Field Admin., circa 1957-1960 (Box 3)
    - Economics, circa 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Marion Logue-county planning, circa 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Department of Political Science, U. Of North Carolina:
    - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 3)
    - Institute of government, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Yale Executive Committee for Social Studies of the University Division of Liberal Arts, 1954-1964 (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1936-1970; Accession 1973-M-002; 2 linear feet (2 paige boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Files pertaining to various committees and boards of Yale University and J. Feeler's work in behalf of the American Political Science Association, the United Nations Working Group on Administrative Decentralization for Development and the President's Committee on Administrative Management.
  - 1. Joint Boards of Permanent Offices: Minutes (Secretary), 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - 2. Graduate School (Box 1)
    General
    a. Faculty meetings
    b. Executive Committee: Minutes, etc., 1965-1968 (Member)
    c. Wilbur L Cross Medal, 1966-1969 (Committee member)
  - 3. University Committee on Summer Programs, 1970-1971 (Member) (Box 1)
  - 4. Joint B.A.-M.A. Program, 1970 (Committee member) (Box 1)
  - 5. Yale College: Combined Science Major, 1967-1970 (Committee member) (Box 1)
  - 6. Concilium on International and Area Studies (Box 1)
    a. Committee for Faculty Research, 1965-1971 (Member)
    b. Council on Comparative and European Studies, 1969-1970 (Member)
  - 7. National Policy Committee (of Yale), 1968 (Member) (Box 1)
  - 8. Department of Political Science: Falk Graduate Fellowships (Box 1)
  - 9. Berkeley College, 1959-1971 (Executive Fellow, 1959-1969) (Box 1)
  - 10. Yale Faculty Club: Committee for Revision of Articles of Incorporation and By-laws (Chairman), 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1. Administrative Reorganization of the Federal Government (Box 2)
    a. 1936: U.S. President's [Brownlow] Committee on Administrative Management—Member of the staff, and author of the Committee's published monograph, Executive Management and the Federal Field Service.
    b. 1948: U.S. [First Hoover] Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government—Consultant to Klein & Saks, the firm the Commission contracted with for a study of the Federal field service.
    c. 1967: U.S. President's [Heineman] Task Force on Government Organization—Consultant, prepared a memorandum, "Departmental and Inter-departmental Field Administration."
  - 2. Developing Countries' Centralized/Decentralized Administration (Box 2)
    -1961: United Nations Working Group on Administrative Decentralization for Development.
    -Member of the Working Group, whose two-week meeting in Geneva contributed toward preparation of United Nations Technical Assistance Programme (Division for Public Administration, Dept. of Economic and Social Affairs), Decentralization for National and Local Development (UN, 1962)
  - 3. American Political Science Association (and national scholarly associations' handling of internal radical protest movement) (Box 2)
    -1969: Vice President of the Association; Chairman of the Procedures Committee; Vice Chairman and Acting Chairman of the (Mail) Elections Committee.
- Additional Material, 1965-1971; Accession 1975-M-001; 1 linear foot (1 paige box)
  This addition consists of one box of records accumulated in connection with James W. Fesler's chairmanship of the Committee on Europe of the Comparative Administration Group. The latter was a substantially autonomous element within the American Society for Public Administration operating under two successive grants from the Ford Foundation for the decade of 1961-1971. The Europe Committee was established in the Fall of 1965 and, with its parent Group, became inactive and died in the early 1970s. The file folders and records use the acronyms "CAG" for Comparative Administration Group and "CAGE" for Comparative Administration Group— Europe.
  Future interest in these records (if any) is likely to turn on this American committee's experience in establishing cross-Atlantic contacts with European scholars and—as it turned out—in promoting communication among the Europeans themselves. The Committee sponsored two international conferences, one in 1966 at Bochum, Heidelberg, and Speyer, Germany, and one in 1968 at Salzburg.
  - Committee Records (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1941-1978; September 1978 Addition; 1.25; (5 boxes)
  - Records acquired by Professor Fesler as a member of the Committee on the Structure of State Government, popularly known as "the Filer Committee." (For further information please see the attached letter), 1976-1978 (Box 1–4)
  - Correspondence, A-K, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, L-Z, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence A-K, 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, L-Z, 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: members of Congress, 1960-1974 (Box 5)
  - War Production Board (WPB) (Box 6)
  - Planning Committee and Office of Production Management Production Planning Board, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
  - WPB Congressional justifications for budget estimates, 1944 (Box 6)
  - National Security Resources Board, notes re: mobilization planning, 1945-1948 (Box 6)
  - Connecticut Constitutional Convention, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Connecticut Citizens Conference on The General Assembly, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - National Science Foundation Fellowship Panel, 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - Committee for Economic Development (CED), 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - (CED)-Committee for Improvement of Management in Government (CIMG), 1968-1972 (Box 6)
  - CED-CIMG, 1970-1973 (Box 6)
  - CED-CIMG, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - U.S. ("Murphy") Commission on Organization of the Government for Conduct of Foreign Policy, 1974 (Box 6)
- Additional Material, 1935-1979; Accession 1980-M-004; 6 linear feet (5 paige boxes, 1 archive, 1 half archive)
  - JWF vitas, publications lists; Non-Yale committees, consultantships, and editorships (Box 1)
  - JWF vitas and publications lists; reviews and fan mail; reprints and translations, 1947-1979 (Box 1)
  - JWF official records (Box 1)
    Yale appointment (1951 et seq.); salary increases; May 9, 1979, retirement dinner and letters; official records of appointments at University of North Carolina (1935-1951); government appointments; positions offered but rejected; pre-Yale course records; miscellany.
  - Non-Yale committees, etc., 1936-1979
    - President's Committee on Administrative Management ("the Browlow Committee", 1936 (Box 1)
    - Consultantship in Vietnam, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Princeton University Department of Politics Advisory Committee, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - University of Connecticut Political Science Department, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Committee on the Structure of State Government (Connecticut) ("the Filer Committee") (Box 1)
    - Impact of Federal Health Policy: Advisory Group, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Senate Subcommittee on Executive Reorganization: Advisory Panel, 1965 (Box 1)
    - American Political Science Association; American Political Science Review Joint Committee on Political Science and Administrative Law, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Washington Social Science Federation, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Miscellany (Box 1)
    - American Society for Public Administration: Public Administration Review (JWF, editor-in-chief, 1958-1960); International Committee, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Public Administration, 1967-1979 (Box 2)
  - Inter-University Case Program, 1959-1978 (Box 2)
  - JWF Manuscripts, etc., 1950-1973 (Box 3)
    (public lectures; encyclopedia articles; Carnegie Corporation research grant; SSRC fellowship; book and article publicatin arrangements)
  - Yale University Committees, etc.; Department of Political Science, 1955-1979 (Box 3)
    - Yale University (President, Provost, Secretary) (Box 3)
    - JWF Memorandum on "Erosion of the Teacher/Scholar Role of Yale Faculty Members", 1970 (Box 3)
    - Social Sciences Advisory/Appointments Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
    - School of Organization and Management (Box 3)
    - Institution for Socialand Policy Studies (Box 3)
    - Yale College--esp. Course of Study Committee, 1975-1976, 1978-1979 (JWF, chairman, 1979) (Box 3)
  - University Library Committee, 1965-1973 (Box 4)
  - Yale University Press Publications Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Berkeley College (Box 4)
  - Department of Political Science
    - Department of Political Science, 1955-1979 (Box 4)
    - Department Staff Appointments (Box 4)
    - Graduate Program (Box 4)
    - Undergraduate Program--esp. Committee on the Future of the Undergraduate Program, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
      (JWF, chairman)
    - Correspondence; Course grade records, syllabi, and students' critiques Dissertations (Box 5)
  - Correspondence:, Pre-1969; 1969-1979 (Box 5)
  - JWF Undergraduate Courses: American Government; Public Administration and Public Policy; Problems of the American Presidency (Box 5)
  - JWF Graduate Courses: The American Presidency; National Governmental Institutions; Public Administration; Comparative Public Administration (Box 5)
  - Dissertations:
    - Dissertations:, 1959-1973, 1974-1979 (Box 6–7)
    - Bruce Buchanan; Donald F. Kettl; Michael J. Landauer (not completed); Edward Pauly; Allen Schick; Carolyn Hughes Tuchy; Jessica Wolf; Douglas T. Yates; Allan Richards (University of North Carolina, 1948) (Box 6–7)
  - "National Security Resources Board (JWF Consultant and pre-NSRB recommendations for its creation)", 1945-1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Yale Club of Washington: list of Yale men in Congress honored at reception, 1958 February 25 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1987-M-046
  - JWF Dissertation, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Soil Conservation Service, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Social Science Research Countil: Committee on Public Administration, 1942 (Box 1)
  - War Production Board, 1942-1945 (Box 1)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower, Remarks, March 13, 1946 (Box 1)
  - (First Hoover) Commission on Reorganization of the Executive Branch, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Study of Field Service of Dept. of Interior, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Economic Stabilization Agency, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut State Government Organization, incl. Filer Committee., 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Elmer Staats: Honorary Degree Proposal, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - "The Institutionalized Presidency and Policy Formation", November 6, 1982 (Box 1)
  - JWF Awards, etc., 1984-1986 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1918-1987; Accession 1988-M-041; 5 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Diane E. Kaplan, 1988 January
  Received from: James W. Fesler
  - Correspondence, 1938-1950 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - African trip memorabilia, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Personal files, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Calendars, appointment books, address books, 1944-1979 (Box 2)
  - Biographical and memorabilia files including letters, clippings, photographs, notes, etc., 1918-1987 (Box 3)
  - Letters: grand tour of Europe, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Civilian Production Administration, Bureau of Demobilization-Historical Reports on War Administration: War Production Board, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1956-1979 (Box 5)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Letters of recommendation are closed until January 1, 2055 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, 1925-1991; Accession 1992-M-081; 1; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1993 Feb
  Received from: James W. Fesler, 1992 Jun 24
  - Papers, 1926-1932
    - High School Orations (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - a. "Lincoln and the Constitution,", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - b. "Lincoln and the Constitution", 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - c. "Abraham Lincoln" (Lincoln's Birthday address) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - d. Text of Daniel Webster's Bunker Hill Address (given on Memorial Day) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - e. "Education for Service," Commencement Oration, June 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - College Papers
      - a. "The Recent Rise of Stocks and Fall of Bonds," Economics term paper, November 21, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - b. "Labor Trouble in Gastonia," Economics term paper, April 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - c. "The Influence of Federalism on National Associations of State Administrative Officials" term paper for Comparative Federalism course, May 16, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - d. "Compulsory Unemployment Insurance," honors paper, May 28, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Graduate School Papers and Publications, 1932-1935
    - 1. "Minority Representation under the American Franchise," Comparative Government course (Mitrany), December 3, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2. "Eliot and Lowell," The Harvard Critic I, (December 15, 1932) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 3. "Charles W. Eliot as an Educational Leader," U.S. Intellectual and Cultural History course (Schlesinger, Sr.), December 22, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 4. "Security" (with D A. Weiss), course paper (Mitrany), March 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 5. "The Political Theory of Du Haillan," Political Theory, Plato to Rousseau course (McIlwain), Apr15, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 6. [not in folder] "The Limitations of Regionalism in French Administration," Comparative government reading course (Friedrich), March 6, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 7. "Sociology and Jurisprudence in the Theory of Léon Duguit," Political theory reading course (Elliott), April 9, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 8. "Regional Decentralization in France and Great Britain," Comparative government reading course (Elliott), June 2, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 9. [not in folder]"Federal Administrative Regions, with special reference to War Department Procurement Planning Activities," Ph.D. dissertation, April 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Volume in Harvard University Library.
  - Publications and Papers, 1935-1936
    - 1. "Regional Developments in European Governments," draft (Summer 1935) of intended but unpublished Appendix D of National Resources Committee, Regional Factors in Planning and Development. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 2. "The Loan of Expert Personnel among Federal Agencies," processed, National Resources Committee, September 9, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 3. "Federal Department Experience," and "Federal Department Procedure," Chapters V and VIII of National Resources Committee Regional Factors in National Planning and Development, (December 1935) (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Volume in Government Documents Collection, Yale University Library.
    - 4. National Resources Planning Board Bulletin R-39, processed, November 18, 1939, re above item (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 5. "Federal Administrative Regions," American Political Science Review, 30 (April 1936) pp. 257-268. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications and Papers, 1936-1939
    - 1. "Report on the Field Service of the National Emergency Council," typescript, President's Committee on Administrative Management, August 8, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2. "Coordination among Federal Agencies," typescript, President's Committee on Administrative Management, September 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 3. "Standardization of Federal Administrative Regions," Social Forces, 13 (October 1936), pp. 12-21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 4. "Executive Management and the Federal Field Service," in President's Committee on Administrative Management, Report with Special Studies (January 1937), pp. 275-294; and in ibid., Problems of Administrative Management (1937), pp. 27-46 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 5. "Organization for Regulation in Wisconsin," typescript for Robert E. Cushman, c. Spring, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 6. "Our Changing Government," prepared for interdepartmental course's materials at University of North Carolina, Circa 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 7. "Interim Progress Report on Study of the Independence of State Regulatory Agencies," typescript for Robert E. Cushman, March-April 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 8. "The Merit System in the States," address to the Public Welfare Institute, processed, October 24, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Publications and Papers, 1940-1943